<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>21st Century Strategy Guide</title><description>A manual to the opportunities of our strange future.</description><link>https://21stcentury.guide</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 19:05:03 -0500</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 19:05:03 -0500</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://21stcentury.guide/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://21stcentury.guide/humans/algorithmically-disposable-people</guid><title>Algorithmically disposable people</title><description>How has software changed labor and the workplace?</description><link>https://21stcentury.guide/humans/algorithmically-disposable-people</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 12:05:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since 2010, a revolution has swept through labor.</p><p>The algorithmically disposable person is someone who makes money by interacting almost exclusively with software. They apply for the work through software, they receive jobs through software. Pay is managed, delivered, and often obscured by software. If one day they fall out of favor, software will inform them they are terminated.</p><p>Examples of the algorithmically disposable person include those who work for rideshare apps, digitally-enabled food delivery services, and even housekeepers. When a company treats you as an ADP, the immediate advantage for the company is legal flexibility. Through legal fictions like terming ADP’s “independent contractors,” companies can save considerable money by not providing protections and benefits traditionally offered to workers.</p><p>But the ADP is more than a legal dodge. You don’t need to look algorithmically disposable people in the eye when you fire them. Companies can offload the difficult conversation of separation to software. When an ADP falls behind on certain measures tracked by software, that software can inform the ADP their services are no longer needed. Thus, workers become rows in a database. With their relationship to a parent company entirely mediated through software, they have limited means of appealing adverse decisions. The software doesn’t talk back, and the company that owns the software can, once they reach a certain scale, quickly replace them.</p><p>Algorithmically disposable people are also vulnerable to wage manipulation. When you have no personal relationships to draw on, and a company has commodified your labor, it is a challenge to effectively negotiate your pay. ADP labor is, from the start, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_form_contract#Contracts_of_adhesion">contract of adhesion</a>. You take it or leave it.</p><p>But whereas the contracts of old have the benefits of clear terms and explicit numbers, algorithmically disposable people must contend with black box calculations of pay. Because they are termed “contractors,” they have limited recourse if pay slides below legal limits for “employees.”</p><p>You may read this and think that the plight of the algorithmically disposable person is unfair. This may be the greatest dark advantage of software-mediated labor. The software is indifferent to fairness, indifferent to kindness, indifferent to suffering. Whereas human supervisors may fudge schedules, pick favorites, or look the other way when a worker is going through a rough patch, software supervisors are consistent and exacting. Software is too simple for empathy.</p><p>Algorithmically disposable people have lost all power in their labor relations. They have been reduced to commodities that produce outcomes. Should those outcomes become unreliable, they are replaced.</p><p>The explosion of ADP-derived labor is a reflection of economic desperation as much as any technological development. In an economy where fair wages and worker security was in abundance, it would be difficult to operate this way. Software is not the root cause of this precarity—merely its lubricant.</p><p>Still, it must be stressed that gig software companies at scale create feedback loops that erode outcomes for workers. Success of these companies creates convenience and profits for a few, insecurity for many.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://21stcentury.guide/resources/how-money-works</guid><title>How money works</title><description>What is money, why do we have it?</description><link>https://21stcentury.guide/resources/how-money-works</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 12:05:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The usual discussion of economics would have you believe it is the study of money. While money is surely essential to any economic conversation, it’s just an abstraction on top of the true interest of economics:</p><p>Energy scarcity.</p><p>Economics is the study of how scarce resources are allocated to keep us alive. The most scarce resource we know of is energy.</p><h2>It begins out there</h2><p>The universe is trying to kill you.</p><p>It’s just not trying all that hard.</p><p>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_law_of_thermodynamics">basic truth of physics</a> is that any concentration of energy will, eventually, diffuse away. Your mug of hot cocoa will lose steam, the sun will burn itself out, and the universe <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heat_death_of_the_universe">will one day go cold</a>.</p><p>You needn’t worry about the sun or the heat death of the universe. We’ll be long dead before those problems arrive. But the hot cocoa is a lot closer to home. It’s an object lesson. Just like the cocoa, one day soon you, too, will go cold.</p><p>The only question is when. You can push that date off further and further by adding and preserving energy within the biological system you call your body.</p><p>Spend too long in the cold, the energy in your body leaches out and you’re dead. Go too long without food, your body spends all its stored energy and you’re dead. Leave a disease unmanaged, your body expends all its energy managing a broken system and, eventually, you’re dead.</p><p>You get the point.</p><p>I don’t mean to be morbid. I only point this out to underscore the importance of economics — that is, our study and management of scarce energy. While economics is steeped in obscure terminology and inaccessible, complex theory, it’s just about as important as your own heartbeat.</p><h2>Basics of energy economics</h2><p>We live on a planet positioned around 93 million miles from a ball of hot plasma we call <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun">Sol</a>. The sun accounts for 99.86% of the mass in our solar system. Most of that is hydrogen, which the sun converts into energy by a process called fusion.</p><p>Sol outputs so much energy, you and I don’t have a meaningful frame of reference for it. After all, this energy is enough to warm up a ball of water and dirt 93 million miles away.</p><p>For as long as humans have been alive, and much longer than that, this basic setup has powered economics on planet earth.</p><p>It works like this:</p><ol><li>Unimaginable quantities of energy leave Sol</li><li>Plants on earth absorb part of that energy in the form of light. Light energy sustains the plants and allows them to grow</li><li>Animals come along and eat the plants. Chemical energy sustains the animals and allows them to grow</li><li>We eat the plants and animals</li></ol><img src="../../uploads/2019/10/1-ohhBKGq6Kel40wYlu1JrEw.png"/><p>Simple, right? Plants and animals are self-sustaining energy storage devices. Ecosystems are biological power plants, fueled by the sun.</p><p>Unique among other life on earth, humans are able to make plans and share them with others. Humans have been harvesting energy from ecosystems for over a hundred thousand years. Most of this time was spent in a process of hunting and foraging inside of existing systems.</p><p>Bands of humans would roam the Earth’s fertile countrysides in search of tasty ecosystems, moving from place to place as circumstances and scarcity demanded.</p><p>But ten thousand years ago, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neolithic_Revolution">something changed</a>.</p><h2>Imposing order</h2><p>Over time, humans discovered that they could build their own simple ecosystems. This event is often called the agricultural revolution. It fundamentally changed human society — and thus, economics.</p><p>Under agriculture, land was seeded with valuable plants and animals. This stock was carefully tended by humans. Instead of roaming, humans found the land that was most productive for farming and stayed there year after year.</p><p>This led to the first permanent settlements — villages, towns and cities.</p><p>Through farming, predictable energy could be harnessed from the sun, leading to the growth of populations who build agricultural settlements. Farming also allowed for free time to enjoy leisure and perform experiments. It necessitated tools for working the fields and tracking inventories.</p><p>Newly abundant energy opened the doors to technological and cultural advancement. Math and writing emerged as critical early systems for managing the agricultural revolution, forming the foundation of everything we think of as civilization even thousands of years later.</p><h2>Resulting chaos</h2><p>While human-accesible energy in the agricultural age was much more abundant than in the past, scarcity still reigned. For one thing, the earth’s surface is 75% water. Of the 25% that’s land, only a fraction is actually usable for agriculture. Factors like elevation, access to water, soil fertility, and overall climate make a huge difference in the agricultural value of any given scrap of land.</p><p>While conflict afflicts all animals, agriculture pushed humanity to perfect war and politics.</p><p>Farming laid the foundation for accomplishing all other work, from mining to pottery to painting. Without a strong agricultural base to feed your population, nothing else was possible.</p><p>While always dressed in various flavors of principle and ideology, war has always been about settling beefs with force. Those beefs are invariably rooted in who gets access to what scarce resource, and under what terms. Ideology was, and remains, a useful means of a creating an <em>other</em>, whose destruction and resource plunder was justified by strangeness of values and culture.</p><p>Because agriculture was so essential to power, it also became the first center of labor injustices. The prosperity of farming was not always shared fairly with those who tended the fields. Indeed, in the United States alone, trillions of dollars in value was created through the forced labor of African slaves. These individuals had no individual liberty. These humans were held as property because they had no political power and their service to agriculture had the potential to create extraordinary wealth.</p><p>Colonialism was also rooted in agricultural exploitation. Colonies were founded on land that was especially fertile, with no consideration paid to indigenous peoples whose use of that land went back generations.</p><p>Even gendered oppression, still rife in the 21st century, has an agricultural basis. Humans were labor power, and women were the source of all humans. Thus, controlling women’s lives through laws, culture and social taboos was essential to controlling the production of agricultural labor power.</p><h2>Next episode</h2><p>Tending to our energy needs has completely shaped human culture.</p><p>And that was even before the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steam_engine">steam engine</a>. With that invention, humanity discovered an extraordinary new direction of converting energy into work. To serve this innovation, we started pulling more and more <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fossil_fuel">fossil fuels</a> out of the ground.</p><p>With the coupling of an old energy source to a new tool to harness it, technological innovation exploded. We call this the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Industrial_Revolution">industrial revolution</a>.</p><p>But was this really a new fuel source? Whether coal, petroleum or natural gas, fossil fuels are the result of ancient plant and animal life. They’re the sun again, stored and concentrated beneath the earth’s surface.</p><img src="../../uploads/2019/10/1-4CBW3es7iVIFOBvqcXeicw.png"/><p>Just like agriculture, fossil fuels are rooted in scarcity. They’re not evenly distributed. They’re not always easy to discover or extract. And unlike plants, once we use up fossil fuels, they’re gone. One day, we’ll run out.</p><p>Still, the energy multiplier of engines and fuels sent humanity hurtling to all new frontiers. While humans can’t directly consume fossil fuels, they’ve nonetheless completely altered agriculture. Machines have automated much of the hard labor necessary to farming. In 1900, 41% of US labor was dedicated to farms. By 2000, that had <strong>dropped to just 2%</strong>.</p><p>US labor, freed from the yoke of the farm, expanded into myriad other industries, from manufacturing finished goods to entertainment to finance. Still, this labor surplus hasn’t been without its downsides. Black communities, disenfranchised by hundreds of years of economic theft, find their young men disproportionately incarcerated. As the need for labor shrinks, populations turn to more and more desperate means of survival.</p><h2>Money == survival credits</h2><p>Money is an abstraction on top of the chain of energy conversion between the sun and you. Because that chain is filled with inefficiencies, risk and adverse politics, there’s not always enough money — enough survival — to go around.</p><p>Which makes survival a struggle. We use money to access the basics necessary to maintain our own energy supply. Food, shelter and clothing are all essential to keeping our systems running. They all cost money.</p><p>It gets complex, too, because there are so many systems layered between ourselves and our means of survival in the 21st century. For example: it’s not just that clothes keep energy from leaching out of our bodies. They also signal to others whether or not we should be allowed to participate in the systems of survival themselves.</p><p>Thus, it’s a lot easier to get more money if you already have some. If you don’t, breaking the cycle of resource scarcity is a lot more challenging. It’s <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/united-states/21663262-why-low-income-americans-often-have-pay-more-its-expensive-be-poor">expensive to be poor</a>.</p><h2>An energy efficiency revolution</h2><p>100 years after the agricultural revolution, humanity sped up even more.</p><p>In the 1970’s, the microprocessor changed everything about how work could be done. Packed with systems of logic, computer chips made information processing a completely automatic affair. Chips could sort data, communicate between systems, and even direct the efforts of robotic manufacturing.</p><p>Chips allowed energy to be converted into work in a way we’d never seen before. Look what happened.</p><p>With this incredible automation of labor, it became possible for a small number of people to keep and hold a vast chunk of economic output. While later policies further contributed to wage stagnation, it is the microprocessor that’s the longest lever in creating 21st century wealth inequality. With more and more industrial processes reducible to something that can be handled by a computer — that is, an object whose entire output can owned — the need to share in wealth creation with other humans continues to shrink.</p><p>Indeed, the most reliably lucrative career direction in the 2010’s has been the work of directing microprocessors to do the bidding of humans. Scarce access to the skills necessary for computer programming has limited the pool of people able to participate in that industry. With scarce labor on one side and enormous riches on the other, many software developers enjoy a uniquely powerful negotiating position that leads to generous pay and often favorable working conditions.</p><p>For now.</p><h2>Surviving until the greatest revolution</h2><p>Exiting energy poverty will be the greatest revolution humanity has ever seen. As more of the sun is harnessed, as new physics is pioneered, we will find energy abundant enough to meet the survival needs of more and more people.</p><p>With energy abundance will come, far down the road, the opportunity for a shared prosperity, safety and global peace like we have never known.</p><p>Until that door is opened, though, we still have to get by. In a life of energy scarcity, the most important strategy is continually building processes for yourself that multiply finite resources to keep you alive.</p><p>While making money through selling labor as a software developer is often provided as an ideal means of economic mobility, that strategy doesn’t go far enough. The most powerful survival tool today is owning a business that’s run with microprocessors.</p><p>Successful digital businesses efficiently convert ideas into software that solves problems, or conveniently deliver digital content that people want to enjoy. In exchange for solving people’s problems, people exchange some of their survival credits. Make people's lives easier, more fun, or more interesting, they'll share some of their survival surplus with you.</p><p>That’s not a bad deal. It’s a deal that lets you build wealth as you sleep.</p><p>So if you want to get by in the 21st century, the point isn't to be a software engineer. Be a digital business engineer. Build a system that delivers non-scarce, digitally-mediated resources that people want.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://21stcentury.guide/humans/range-of-motion</guid><title>Range of motion</title><description>Range of motion: the boosters and barriers for moving through life.</description><link>https://21stcentury.guide/humans/range-of-motion</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 12:05:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The universe imposes limits. Even light has a maximum speed.</p><p>Our human universe is similarly constrained. It is possible to accomplish extraordinary things, but rarely all at once. Success in life is governed by your ability to make plans to cross the gulf between where you are and where you want to go.</p><p>Consider an airplane. It can take you extraordinary distances, but it can't fly forever. For a long enough journey, the plane must land, refuel, and perhaps change crews before continuing onward. Not all planes are created equal. Smaller planes have shorter limits before they need refueling. Larger planes can carry you further without interruption.</p><p>I call this idea, when applied to human beings, <em>range of motion</em>. The strategies you need to reach the places you want to go in life will be determined by your range of motion. But even if you feel hopelessly limited by your current range of motion, don't fear: it can be changed.</p><p>To understand how, let's begin by understanding some of the parameters that define your starting position.</p><h2>Bonuses and penalties to range of motion</h2><h3>Wealth</h3><p>The most obvious bonus to range of motion is access to wealth. With enough money, many problems become easy to solve. US$500 might get you from Cape Town to Mumbai if you're willing to wait until next week to leave. But if you're able to pay US$500,000, you can probably leave this afternoon. The advantage of money is that so many people need it, creating opportunities to exchange it with those who have the knowledge, equipment and spare time to solve your problems for you.</p><p>The downside of money is that not everyone has enough of it. Being broke limits your range of motion by limiting the number of problems you can easily solve. Things as mundane as eating lunch, having childcare, or staying warm at night are most easily solved with money. Its absence quickly gets in the way.</p><p>It’s possible to increase your access to wealth if you’re starting without much of it. But to do so, you’ll need to increase your range of motion in other ways.</p><h3>Knowledge</h3><p>Luckily, there are other means of boosting your range of motion.</p><p>Perhaps more pivotal than money, over the long term, is knowledge, whether acquired through formal education or through more practical experience. Knowledge allows you to imagine solutions to both your own problems, and to the problems of others. This may also be a path to having more money when starting with less. By having knowledge that others need, you can exchange that knowledge for money. But even without direct financial exchange, the right knowledge on its own will take you far. Knowledge lets you know when you're being lied to. Knowledge lets you understand how things work, giving you a starting point to make them work better.</p><p>Knowledge is also more accessible today than at any other time in human history. The importance of knowledge to range of motion, coupled with the modern ease of acquiring that knowledge, is the greatest opportunity available today. This fact is also one of the central motivators of this book. Take it seriously.</p><h3>Relationships</h3><p>Less democratic than knowledge, but even more powerful as an amplifier to range of motion, are relationships. Relationships create opportunities to gain knowledge, trade favors, access wealth, and join new communties. Relationships open doors that can lead to shortcuts on the path to your goals.</p><p>Relationships are often tangled up with other factors in your range of motion. Pursuing knowledge at an elite school will create relationships with other people who have an elite education. Because elite schools are so often populated by the wealthy, you may find that relationships with those who attended also bring you closer to wealth. Similarly, those born with wealth will inherit more relationships to other wealthy people than those who were born broke. This generational feedback loop is one of the factors that creates age-old complaint that “the rich get richer.”</p><p>If there’s something you want but don’t have, you have a better chance of finding a path to it the more relationships you’ve cultivated.</p><h3>Skills</h3><p>Related to knowledge, skills define the things you can do. These range from the creative to the practical, everything from drawing to singing to sewing to building cabinets. While knowledge informs many skills, they’re not just about what you know.</p><p>Skills are also about what you have practiced. The more time invested in a skill, the more effective you become at it. Because of this, skills are intertwined with another, crucial factor: spare time.</p><h3>Spare Time</h3><p>With spare time, you can invest in knowledge, develop new skills, further refine existing skills, pursue new relationships, and deepen existing relationships. Without spare time, it can be challenging to move forward toward your goals.</p><p>But what is spare time? It’s the time you have that isn’t already claimed by something essential to the survival of yourself or someone else. If you work long hours, you’ll be shorter on spare time than someone who doesn’t have to work, or works only part of the day or week.</p><h3>Social prejudices</h3><p>For some of us, social prejudices confer advantages to range of motion. “Prejudice” is a word with negative connotations, so it may be confusing to see it described as advantageous. The negative connotation comes from how unfair and arbitrary that pre-judgement is.</p><p>In many cultures, having a particular gender, skin color, romantic preference, or even last name can cause someone to judge you as more capable, intelligent or trustworthy compared to those who are different from you. Even arbitrary things like a person’s height can contribute positively, or negatively, to their perceived abilities as a leader.</p><p>Social prejudices may be the most frustrating factor in range of motion because we have the least control over them. You can work hard to acquire knowledge, develop relationships, even save money. But there is a limit to how much you can overcome social prejudices from moment to moment. These prejudices may permanently close doors to you, impose limits on the relationships you can develop, and act as a constant source of friction on the way to your goals.</p><p>Or, they may give you a constant, gentle, forward tug.</p><p>It’s completely arbitrary.</p><p>If you feel the friction of social prejudice in your own adventures, know that all is not lost. Adversity demands creativity. The reward for overcoming and outmaneuvering these arbitrary obstacles is greater resilience, more imaginative strategy, and a broader insight into the journeys of those around you. Those who win easily often do not understand the source of their accomplishments. Those who must plot their course thoughtfully can see the systems around them more clearly, finding themselves better able to discern between luck and hard work.</p><h3>Physical ability and cognition</h3><p>Range of motion takes on a literal dimension when we consider physical ability. Much of the world is built for those who are considered “able-bodied,” with meager considerations offered to the needs of those who differ from that expectation. In many ways, this is an extension of the social prejudices described above, but it can take on more concrete forms. Lack of thought for how a product, service or facility will meet the needs of those with different physical abilities or specific medical needs can entirely exclude people from easily meeting their goals—again, for entirely arbitrary reasons.</p><p>Even having a mind which works differently from what people expect can impact your range of motion. The ability to read social cues or otherwise comfortably participate in social interactions is an enormous advantage—and its absence a powerful disadvantage. Laboring beneath the weight of depression, anxiety or other afflictions of the mind can limit your ability to pursue and maintain focus on your goals.</p><h2>Increasing range of motion</h2><p>Some factors in your range of motion will feel stubbornly fixed. You can’t immediately change people’s social prejudices, and the changes you can make to your physical abilities are limited. You can’t choose to be born to a wealthy family. You may even find your spare time constrained by other responsibilities in your life.</p><p>Still, there are factors that are more malleable. With a bit of discipline, for regular investment, and creativity, to solve the problems of making those investments possible, you <em>can</em> increase your range of motion. Knowledge, skills and relationships can all be cultivated to improve your changes of meeting your goals.</p><p>The more investment made in increasing range of motion, the greater the returns. As you develop skills and knowledge, you’ll find more relationships with people who need you to solve their problems. With consistency and luck, this can turn into money—and deeper skills, sharper knowledge, developed from the time you’re paid to solve people’s problems. With more money comes more options for spare time, and thus more opportunity to invest in further skills and knowledge, more space to develop new relationships.</p><p>And so on.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>